Guide to the Boswell Collection Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Administration of estates -- Scotland; British -- India; Entail -- Scotland; Family farms -- Scotland; Farm management -- Scotland; Farm tenancy -- Economic aspects -- Scotland; Inheritance and succession -- Scotland; Land tenure -- Scotland; Manors -- Scotland; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Plantation life -- India; Plantation life -- Jamaica -- History; Slave trade -- Great Britain; Slaveholders -- Jamaica; Slavery -- Jamaica; Ayrshire (Scotland); Great Britain -- Rural conditions; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947; Jamaica -- Economic conditions; Jamaica -- History -- Maroon War, 1795-1796; Jamaica -- History -- To 1962; Scotland -- Economic conditions; Boswell, Alexander, Sir, 1775-1822; Boswell, Hamilton Douglas; Boswell, James, 1806-1857; Boswell, James, 1740-1795; Boswell, Patrick Charles Douglas; Douglas, Charles, 1815; Gibb, Andrew; Gibson, Thomas, 1865-1941
- Correspondence, 1778-1886; Series I; 3.5' linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Boswell of Auchinleck Family, Douglas of Garallan Family, and Committees for the Estate of Auchinleck. Within each subseries, material is arranged first by family generation and then alphabetically by correspondent. Where there are both incoming and outgoing letters for a correspondent, the material has been divided accordingly into these categories; otherwise, all correspondence is incoming.
  - BOSWELL OF AUCHINLECK FAMILY
    - James Boswell (1745-95)
      - Gibb, Andrew (for James Boswell) to Lord Mountstuart, 1793 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Kennedy, John (for Lord Mountstuart) to Andrew Gibb, 1793 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Sir Alexander Boswell (1775-1822)
      - Boswell, Alexander, W. S., 1813-21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sir James Boswell (1807-1857)
      - Outgoing Correspondence
        - Hurd and Johnstone, 1828 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Mitchell, Logan, 1829 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Rankin, Thomas, 1831 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Unidentified (in the matter of Sir William Forbes), 1832 Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Incoming Correspondence
        - Boswell, Alexander, W. S., 1828-32 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Boswell, Jane Douglas, 1831-33, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Campbell, William Bowie, 1836 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Carnegie, Mrs. C., 1832 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Clark, William, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Dicksons and Co., 1829 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Gibb, Andrew, 1830 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - Hamilton, Alexander, 1827-33 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
          With: copy letters forwarded by Hamilton to Sir James Boswell
        - Horne, D., 1829 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Hunters, Co., 1832 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - Johnstone, Quin, 1836 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - Macdowall, William, 1832 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - McGaan, Andrew, 1833 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - Mitchell, Logan, 1829 Aug (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - Murray, John, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Rankin, Thomas, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - Richardson, John, [1829 Jan] (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - Roxburgh, M., 1832 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - Scott, John, 1857 Jul 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - Tilbury, Sons & Clarke, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - Tods and Romanes, 1830-33 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
        - Unidentified covers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Thomas Gibson (factor of Auchinleck)
      - Outgoing Correspondence
        - Boswell, Alexander, W.S., 1826 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
        - Committee of Creditors (circular letters), 1824-25 (Box 1, Folder 34)
          With: note to Lady Boswell, 1824 Dec 27
        - Dallas, A., 1825, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 35)
        - Hamilton, Alexander, 1824-27 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        - Nisbit, Matthew, 1825 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 37)
        - Sloan, William, 1824 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Incoming Correspondence
        - Arrowsmith, Mary (Mrs. John Robson), 1824 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 39)
        - Boswell, Alexander, W. S., 1824-27 (Box 1, Folder 40)
        - Boswell, Grace, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
        - Cannan, Horatius, 1823-25 (Box 1, Folder 42)
        - Colville, James, 1824 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
        - Cuming, J., n.y. Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 44)
        - Dallas, Alexander, 1824-26 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        - Dick, John, 1825 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 46)
        - Edgar, Andrew, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 47)
        - Gibb, Andrew, 1824 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 48)
        - Hamilton, Alexander, 1824-28 (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
        - [Hyslop?], William, 1827 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 51)
        - Johnston, Elizabeth, 1824, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 52)
        - Lambie, William, 1824 Jun 2 (Box 2, Folder 53)
        - McGaan, John, 1828 Aug 30 (Box 2, Folder 54)
        - McGann, Mrs., 1825 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 55)
        - Murdoch, William, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 56)
        - Pagan, William, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 57)
        - Peden, James, 1824 Jun 3 (Box 2, Folder 58)
        - Rankin, Thomas, 1824 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 59)
        - Reid, William, 1824 Jun 21 (Box 2, Folder 60)
        - Renton and Grant, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 61)
        - Robertson, William, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 62)
        - Scrivener, George Scrivener, Mary, 1826-29 (Box 2, Folder 63)
          With: copy of letter from unidentified to Mary Scrivener, 1828 Dec 18
        - Simson, Patrick, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 64)
        - Straehorn, John, 1824 Jun 1 (Box 2, Folder 65)
        - Strathdee, John, 1825, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 66)
        - Stirling, John, 1824 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 67)
        - Tennant, John, 1827 Mar 21 (Box 2, Folder 68)
        - Tods and Romanes, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 69)
        - Weir, John, 1826 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Related Correspondence
      This section contains third-party correspondence referring to Thomas Gibson's tenure as factor of the Auchinleck estate.
      - Bickerston, W. to Tods and Romanes, 1842 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - Boswell, Alexander, W. S. to John Sloan, 1822 Sep 3 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Boswell, Grace to Thomas Rankin, 1826 Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - Colville, James to Thomas Rankin, 1830 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - Gibb, Andrew to Thomas Rankin, 1830 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Hamilton, Alexander
        - to Patrick Simpson, 1825 Mar 21 (Box 2, Folder 76)
        - to Andrew Gibb, 1822 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 77)
        - to John Sloan, 1822-23 (Box 2, Folder 78)
        - to Tods and Romanes, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - Hamilton, John to John Boswell, 1798, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Lamson, Will to Alexander Hamilton, 1824 Apr 28 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - Lindsay, John to unidentified, 1825 Jan 5 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - McGann, John to Alexander Hamilton, 1824 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - McLachlan, Alexander to Alexander Boswell, W. S., 1822, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - Rankin, Thomas
        - to Alexander Boswell, W. S., [1822 May] (Box 2, Folder 85)
        - to Andrew Gibb, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 86)
        - to Tods and Romanes, 1830 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 87)
        - to Unidentified, 1828 Jun 19, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 88)
      - Reid, William to Alexander Hamilton, 1824 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - Robertson, John to Tods and Romanes, 1829 Aug 4 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - Robertson, William to Mr. Rankin, 1828 Oct 16 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - Sloan, John
        - to Alexander Hamilton, 1822 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 92)
        - to the Committee of Creditors, 1822, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      - Sloan, William to John Sloan, 1823 Feb 24 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - Strathdee, John to John Sloan, 1826 Sep 12 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Tods and Romanes
        - to Alexander Hamilton, 1832 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 96)
        - to Hunter, Campbell and Cathcart, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Walker, Richardson and Melville to Alexander Boswell, W. S., 1830 Jul 20 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Woodrow, Andrew to Scott, David, 1808 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Unidentified to Alexander Boswell, W. S., 1824, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - DOUGLAS OF GARALLAN FAMILY
    - Patrick Douglas
      - Bell, Alexander, 1778-83 (Box 2, Folder 101-103)
      - Campbell, Donald, 1784 Aug 28 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      - Campbell of Netherplace, Mrs., 1791 Apr 19 (Box 2, Folder 105)
      - Charles Herries and Co., 1790 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      - [Clocher?], Alexander, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      - Dalrymple, William, 1784 Oct 22 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      - Douglas, Charles, 1783-98 (Box 3, Folder 109-127)
      - Douglas, Charles, 1799-1813 (Box 4, Folder 128-147)
      - Douglas, Charles (nephew of Patrick Douglas), 1818 Jan 9 (Box 4, Folder 148)
      - Douglas, Jane, 1796 Jul 30 (Box 5, Folder 149)
      - Edmiston, John, 1803 Jun 14 (Box 5, Folder 150)
      - Home, Douglas
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Series V, Box 21, folders 629-31
      - McKnight, John, 1808 Feb 12 (Box 5, Folder 151)
      - McWhinnie, Hugh, 1802, 1803 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      - Naismith, Robert, 1786-93 (Box 5, Folder 153-157)
    - Hamilton Douglas Boswell (d. 1824)
      Correspondence of Jane Douglas Boswell, H. D. Boswell's wife and successor as Executrix, is also filed in this subseries.
      - Outgoing Correspondence
        - Boswell, Alexander, W.S. from Jane Douglas Boswell, 1832 Jun 29 (Box 5, Folder 158)
        - Bell, John, 1823-24 (Box 5, Folder 159)
        - Dannan, John, 1823 (Box 5, Folder 160)
        - Hamilton, Alexander, 1823 Dec 23 (Box 5, Folder 161)
        - Lambie, William, 1824 Apr 5 (Box 5, Folder 162)
        - Limond, David, 1814 Nov 13 (Box 5, Folder 163)
        - Paisley, H. J., 1823 Aug 2 (Box 5, Folder 164)
      - Incoming Correspondence
        - Anderson, Ann to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1823 Aug 29 (Box 5, Folder 165)
        - Bell, John, 1823-24 (Box 5, Folder 166)
        - Bell, John to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1824-34 (Box 5, Folder 167-170)
        - Blair, David H., Sir, 1822, 1823 (Box 5, Folder 171)
        - Boswell, Alexander (W. S.), 1809-23 (Box 5, Folder 172-174)
        - Boswell, Alexander (W. S.) to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1825-32 (Box 5, Folder 175)
        - Boswell, Sir James to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1831-32, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 176)
          With: copies in Boswell's hand of business letters to third parties
        - Boswell, Grizel Grace, 1822, 1823 (Box 5, Folder 177)
        - Boswell, Grizel Grace to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1823-25, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 178)
        - Boswell, Jessie Jane, 1823 May 3 (Box 5, Folder 179)
        - Boswell, John Douglas to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1825-34 (Box 5, Folder 180)
        - Boswell, Patrick to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1824 Jun 16 (Box 5, Folder 181)
        - [Bremner?], James, 1822, 1825 (Box 5, Folder 182)
        - Campbell, William Bowie to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1833 Feb 28 (Box 5, Folder 183)
        - Cannan, Horatius, 1823, 1824 (Box 5, Folder 184)
        - Cuninghame, James Montgomery, 1822-24 (Box 6, Folder 185)
        - Dallas, A., 1823 Nov 3 (Box 6, Folder 186)
        - Donnan, John to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1815 Dec 19 (Box 6, Folder 187)
        - Douglas, Charles, 1819 Jan 22 (Box 6, Folder 188)
        - Douglas, Patrick, 1809-18, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 189)
        - Douglas, Patrick to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1799-1819 (Box 6, Folder 190)
        - Edgar, Andrew, 1824 Feb 14 (Box 6, Folder 191)
        - Eliott, Janet Theresa, 1822, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 192)
        - Galbreath, William (also signed by George McCartney), 1834 Dec 15 (Box 6, Folder 193)
        - Gibb, Andrew, 1823-24 (Box 6, Folder 194)
        - Gibson, Thomas to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1824 (Box 6, Folder 195)
        - Gray, James to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1816 Apr 27 (Box 6, Folder 196)
        - Hamilton, Alexander, 1822-24 (Box 6, Folder 197-199)
        - Hamilton, Alexander to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1832-33 (Box 6, Folder 200)
        - Hamilton, [John?], 1807 Jul (Box 6, Folder 201)
        - Hamilton, William, 1816 Feb 29 (Box 6, Folder 202)
        - Hamilton, William to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1815 May 27 (Box 6, Folder 203)
        - Hood of Hudston, William, 1823 Dec 8 (Box 6, Folder 204)
        - Hunter, A. to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1832 Mar 15 (Box 6, Folder 205)
        - Johnstone, Quin to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1836 (Box 6, Folder 206)
        - Kippen and Lindsay, 1815 Nov 29 (Box 6, Folder 207)
        - Lambie, William, 1823 Oct 10 (Box 6, Folder 208)
        - Lambie, William to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1824-32 (Box 6, Folder 209)
        - McWhinnie, Hugh to Jane Douglas Boswell, 1809 Jun 15 (Box 6, Folder 210)
        - Paisley, H. J., 1823 Jun 10 (Box 6, Folder 211)
        - Peile, Thomas Hanson, 1839-42 (Box 6, Folder 212)
        - Richardson, John, 1823 Sep 26 (Box 6, Folder 213)
        - Sloan, John, 1823 Nov (Box 6, Folder 214)
        - Stewart, William, 1824 Mar 12 (Box 6, Folder 215)
        - Steel, John, 1815, 1816 (Box 6, Folder 216)
        - Strathdee, John, 1823 (Box 6, Folder 217)
        - Tennant, John, 1823 (Box 6, Folder 218)
        - Tods and Romanes, 1823 Dec 20 (Box 6, Folder 219)
        - William Sims and Sons, 1821 Jun 19 (Box 6, Folder 220)
        - Wilson, Robert Syon, 1823 (Box 6, Folder 221)
        - Windsor, William, 1823 Aug 23 (Box 6, Folder 222)
        - Woodhouse, Archibald, 1821 Jan 8 (Box 6, Folder 223)
        - Fragments and unidentified, 1824-36, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 224)
    - John Douglas Boswell (1811-1863)
      - Anderson and Murray, 1854 Aug 19 (Box 6, Folder 225)
      - Blair, Patrick, 1834 Mar 8 (Box 6, Folder 226)
      - Boswell, Bruce, 1839 Mar 29 (Box 6, Folder 227)
      - Boswell, Grace, 1844 May 18 (Box 6, Folder 228)
      - Boswell, Sir James, 1833-54, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 229-230)
      - Boswell, Jane Douglas, 1830-33, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 231-232)
      - Brown, Thomas, 1832-34 (Box 6, Folder 233)
      - Campbell, Arthur, 1833 Jan 10 (Box 6, Folder 234)
      - Campbell, William Bowie, 1832-43 (Box 7, Folder 235-242)
      - Cannan, Horatius, 1832-35 (Box 7, Folder 243)
      - Court, John, 1842, 1845 (Box 7, Folder 244)
      - Cowan, Donald, 1835 Apr 23 (Box 7, Folder 245)
      - Cowan, Hugh, 1834 Dec 5 (Box 7, Folder 246)
      - Cowper, William, 1832-34 (Box 7, Folder 247)
      - Crichton, Adam, 1835 Nov 12 (Box 7, Folder 248)
      - Dow and Cowper, 1832-35 (Box 7, Folder 249)
      - Dunn, Thomas, 1838 Jan 27 (Box 7, Folder 250)
      - Dyncock, John and William, 1832-39 (Box 7, Folder 251-253)
      - Eliott, Janet Theresa Boswell, 1834 Oct 24 (Box 7, Folder 254)
      - Farquhar, James, 1836 May 16 (Box 7, Folder 255)
      - Gairdner, C. D., 1834 Nov 11 (Box 7, Folder 256)
      - Grant, Joseph, 1832-34 (Box 7, Folder 257-258)
      - Hamilton, Alexander, 1832-34 (Box 7, Folder 259)
      - Hunter, Campbell and Cathcart, 1832-37 (Box 7, Folder 260)
      - Ingram, Andrew, 1833 Dec 25 (Box 7, Folder 261)
      - Jameson, Melville, 1835 Oct 22 (Box 7, Folder 262)
      - Johnston, Elizabeth, 1834, 1835 (Box 7, Folder 263)
      - Johnstone, Quin, 1836-39 (Box 7, Folder 264)
      - Lindsay, Janet, 1833 Apr 22 (Box 7, Folder 265)
      - [Lyon?], John S., 1834 Aug 25 (Box 7, Folder 266)
      - McClelland, George, 1835-36 (Box 7, Folder 267)
      - McKenzie, John W., 1842-63 (Box 8, Folder 268-287)
      - Mitchell, Logan, 1833 Apr 15 (Box 9, Folder 288)
      - Montgomerie, M., 1842 (Box 9, Folder 289)
      - Morton, James, 1838 (Box 9, Folder 290)
      - Nichol, Alex, 1834 (Box 9, Folder 291)
      - Paterson, Adam, 1839-54 (Box 9, Folder 292-294)
      - [Railton?], John, 1833 Jan 7 (Box 9, Folder 295)
      - Richardson, Thomas, 1828-36 (Box 9, Folder 296)
      - Robertson, John, 1837-38 (Box 9, Folder 297)
      - Robertson, William, 1834, 1842 (Box 9, Folder 298)
      - Robson, Will Frogat, 1839 (Box 10, Folder 299)
      - Roxburgh, Mrs., 1832 Jun 8 (Box 10, Folder 300)
      - Russel, Hamilton, 1833-37 (Box 10, Folder 301-303)
      - Samson, J., 1834 (Box 10, Folder 304)
      - Scott and Gillespie, 1851-54 (Box 10, Folder 305)
      - Scott-Moncrieff and Dalgety, 1859 (Box 10, Folder 306)
      - Simson, Patrick, 1833 (Box 10, Folder 307)
        With: Samson, W. to William Bones, 1833 May 8
      - Smith, William, 1834 Jan 1 (Box 10, Folder 308)
      - Strathdee, John, 1850, 1851 (Box 10, Folder 309)
      - Tods and Romanes, 1832-54 (Box 10, Folder 310)
    - Patrick Charles Douglas Boswell (1815?-1892)
      Correspondence of Annabella Innes Boswell, wife of P. C. D. Boswell, is also filed in this subseries.
      - Outgoing Correspondence
        - Boswell, Hamilton Douglas, 1880-84, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 311-312)
      - Incoming Correspondence
        - Andrew Melrose & Co. to Annabella Innes Boswell, 1884 Jul 19 (Box 10, Folder 313)
        - Boswell, Hamilton Douglas to Annabella Innes Boswell, 1880-86, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 314-317)
        - Boswell, Hamilton Douglas, 1880-86 (Box 10, Folder 318-323)
        - Dunlop, Douglas to ? Douglas, 1883, 1885 (Box 10, Folder 324)
        - Dunlop, W. H., 1883-85 (Box 10, Folder 325)
        - Muir, John, 1883 Aug 25 (Box 10, Folder 326)
        - Murray, P. S., 1883 Sep 7 (Box 10, Folder 327)
  - COMMITTEES FOR THE ESTATE OF AUCHINLECK
    This section contains retained copies of correspondence sent in the name of the Committees for the Entailed and the Unentailed Estate of Auchinleck. The letters are arranged chronologically.
    - Copy letters, 1822-35 (Box 11, Folder 328-340)
- Estate Papers, 1774-1881; Series II; 1.0' linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series II, Estate Papers, is organized into two subseries, Auchinleck Estate and Ochiltree Estate. Material within each is arranged alphabetically by type, and therein chronologically. In addition, land records are filed first by name of property and then chronologically. A small group of miscellaneous papers relating to Auchinleck is filed at the end of Auchinleck Estate subseries and is arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - AUCHINLECK ESTATE
    - Accounts
      - "Andrew Gibb. Account with Sir William Forbes, Bart., Executor of the late James Boswell, Esq.", 1795
        See: Oversize, Box 28, folder 786
      - "View of the Produce of the Estate of Auchinleck, Entailed and Unentailed, for 1818, 1819, 1820, & 1821 and of the Produce expected for 1822"
        See: Oversize, Box 28, folder 787
      - Work wages and servants' wages at Auchinleck, 1822 (Box 12, Folder 341)
      - Rentals on the entailed and unentailed estate of Auchinleck, 1822-27 (Box 12, Folder 342)
      - Rentals on the unentailed estate, 1822-33 (Box 12, Folder 343-348)
        See also: Oversize, Box 28, folders 788-89
      - Rental abatements on the unentailed estate of Auchinleck, 1822-24 (Box 12, Folder 349)
      - Rental arrears on the farms of Auchinleck, [1823?] (Box 12, Folder 350)
      - Valuations of the farms in arrears, 1823 (Box 12, Folder 351)
      - Incumbrances and securities on the lands of Auchinleck, 1823-31 (Box 12, Folder 352-353)
      - Sales of wood upon the lands of the unentailed estate of Auchinleck, 1824-28 (Box 12, Folder 354)
      - Factory accounts of the personal and heritable estate, 1827
        See: Oversize, Box 28, folders 790-92
      - Intromissions by the factors on the entailed and unentailed estate, 1828-60 (Box 12, Folder 355-363)
      - Miscellaneous account pages, 1833, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 364)
    - Receipts
      - Rent, 1824-29 (Box 13, Folder 365)
      - Repairs and thatching, 1824-34, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 366)
      - Payments on accounts, 1825-30, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 367)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Articles of roup for farms on the unentailed estate of Auchinleck, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 368)
      - Conditions of tacks on the unentailed estate (Box 13, Folder 369)
      - Draft of lease of farms on Auchinleck estate, 1827 (Box 13, Folder 370)
      - "Draft: Articles and regulations to be observed by the tenants of the estate of Auchinleck", printed form, 1881 (Box 13, Folder 371)
      - Extract minutes of an 1822 meeting of the heritors of Auchinleck, 1824 Jan 26 (Box 13, Folder 372)
      - Extract minutes of a meeting of the Committee of Trustees for the Galson district of Roads, 1826 Jul 15 (Box 13, Folder 373)
      - Lists of tenants upon the unentailed estate, 1832, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 374)
      - Measure of parks at Auchinleck, 1831 (Box 13, Folder 375)
      - Parish burdens on the unentailed estate, 1830 (Box 13, Folder 376)
      - Particulars of the Drainage of Auchinleck, 18[57?]
        See: Oversize, Box 28, folder 793
      - Valuations, inventories and announcements in connection with the sale of the unentailed lands, 1833-41, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 378-380)
        Includes printed legal documents in reference to the Judicial Sale
  - OCHILTREE ESTATE
    - Barony Records
      - Progress of the writs
        - Disposition and sasine of the lands of Dejore and others by the Countess of Glencairn to James Baird in liferent, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 381)
        - Disposition and sasine of Upper Clydenock and others by the Countess of Glencairn to Quintegern (Mungo) Smith in liferent, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 382)
        - Disposition and sasine of Glenconner and Barlosh by the Countess of Glencairn to John Rutherford, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 383)
        - Disposition and sasine of Bent and others by the Countess of Glencairn to William Cunninghame in liferent, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 384)
        - Disposition and sasine of the lands of Creoch and others by the Countess of Glencairn to the Rev. John Robertson, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 385)
        - Disposition and sasine of Wester-Tarbeg and others by the Countess of Glencairn to Haughton Bowman in liferent, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 386)
        - Disposition and sasine of the lands of Tarelgins and others by the Countess of Glencairn to Alexander Mollison, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 387)
        - Disposition and sasine of the lands of Auchinbay by the Countess of Glencairn to Mr. William Creech, 1774 Feb (Box 13, Folder 388)
        - Extract disposition of Upper Clydnock and others by the Countess of Glencairn to James Earl of Glencairn, 1779 Jul 30 (Box 13, Folder 389)
        - Extract charter of resignation by James Earl of Glencairn of parts of Ochiltree, 1779 Aug 6 (Box 14, Folder 390)
        - Disposition of the lands of Clydenock and others by James Earl of Glencairn to Sir Alexander Don in liferent, 1779 Aug 16 (Box 14, Folder 391)
        - Disposition of parts of the barony of Ochiltree by James Earl of Glencairn to James McCrae of Houston, 1779 Aug 16 (Box 14, Folder 392)
        - Instrument of sasine for Upper Clydenock for Sir Alexander Don, 1779 Sep 9 (Box 14, Folder 393)
        - Instrument of sasine for parts of Ochiltree for James McCrae, 1779 Sep 9 (Box 14, Folder 394)
        - Resignation of liferent superiority granted by James McCrae in favor of the Countess of Glencairn, 1786 Feb 20 (Box 14, Folder 395)
        - Renunciation of liferent on parts of Ochiltree by James McCrae in favor of the Countess of Glencairn, 1791 Mar 31 (Box 14, Folder 396)
        - Renunciation of liferent on parts of Ochiltree by Malcolm Fleming in favor of the Countess of Glencairn, 1791 Mar 31 (Box 14, Folder 397)
        - Tacks and liferent renunciations for farms in Ochiltree granted by the Countess of Glencairn, 1787-1823 (Box 14, Folder 398-402)
        - Assignation of tack by John Samson to Jean, Margaret and Jacobina Samson in liferent, 1833 Oct 22 (Box 14, Folder 403)
    - Estate Papers
      - Reports on farms in Ochiltree, 1823, 1831 (Box 14, Folder 404)
      - Memorandum of rental arrears in Ochiltree, [1824] (Box 14, Folder 405)